In this last part of the lecture,
let's focus on how the OS itself can
act as an arbitrator to avoid deadlocks.
In the examples we have seen so far, all the
threads trying to access shared resources sort
of know each other, they share variables, they
have clear roles (e.g., readers and writers),
and so on. But the threads accessing
resources on a computer might be
unaware of which other threads are running, what
resources the latter want to access, and so on...
In this sense, the OS needs to monitor
everything that is happening and,
if it detects that the requests of
a thread could lead to a deadlock,
do something about it, for instance,
decide to schedule the execution of
such a thread for later on.
We are going to introduce a
model for this setup and also mention the
Banker's algorithm (introduced by Dijkstra).
Let's begin with the system model,
which in this case relies on a graph.
In this graph, we have two types of
vertexes: resources and processes
(this is a bipartite graph).
A resource can refer to CPU,
memory, I/O devices, and so on.
Each resource Ri has Wi instances
Since this is a graph, we also have edges.
Each edge connects a Resource with a Process.
If the edge/arrow starts at the process and
ends at a Resource, it means the process is
requesting the resource. If the edge/arrow starts
at a resource and ends at a process, it means the
resource is assigned to the process.
In the case of a request edge,
we use a dashed line to differentiate an
actual request from a potential request
(i.e., a dashed line implies the process might
request the resource but has not done yet).
In our model, besides knowing which resources and
processes we have, and how many instances we have,
we also know the maximum number of instances
each process may need for a given resource.
When it comes to the OS, the idea is that the OS
should be able to distinguish which portion of its
decision space is safe and which is not (in other
words, which decisions might lead to a deadlock).
If, by deciding to give control to
a certain process, the OS allows
for such a process to request a resource
instance that can lead to a deadlock,
then what the OS can do is to instead suspend
such a process, until enough resources are freed.
Suppose for instance we are in this situation:
processes P1 and P2 could be executed next.
Currently, R1 has been given to P1 and P2
has requested R1. The OS also knows that
both P1 and P2 might request R2. Which
process is safe to run next? P1 or P2?
If the OS decides to run P1,
P1 might request and get R2,
which is not leading to any deadlock (so from a
safe state the OS switches to another safe state).
If the OS decides to run P2, P2 might
request and get R2, which in this case
creates a circular loop, and this might
mean deadlock (so from a safe state the
OS switches to an unsafe state)
Based on these observations,
the OS can decide to run P1 and maybe suspend
P2 until such a situation can no longer happen.
For the model we introduced, Dijkstra
introduced an algorithm for resource
allocation that can avoid deadlocks.
The idea is to maintain three data structures:
a matrix called max, that in each position
i j contains the maximum number of instances
process i can request for resource j
a matrix called allocation, that in each
position i j contains the number of instances
already allocated to process i of resource j
an array called available, that in position
j contains the number of instances that are
still available for resource j.
As mentioned before, the idea is
to check whether potentially satisfying
a request can lead to an unsafe state.
How is the check done? By checking whether, by
satisfying a request, the other processes can
still obtain all the resources they might request
or not. If that is the case, the request can be
satisfied, otherwise, the requesting process is
suspended until enough resources are free-ed.
Please notice that the OS has an alternative
to prevent a deadlock from happening:
that of being able to detect a deadlock
as happened and then resolve it.
In other words, the OS can decide to
be reactive rather than proactive.
In that case, there can be two ways out.
The first one is to terminate the process
that has caused a deadlock. Eventually,
once one or more processes are terminated,
enough resources will be available and the
remaining processes will be able to continue.
The second option is to select victim
processes and rollback their execution,
basically go back in their execution to a point
in which the requests made by them did not result
in a deadlock and start again their execution
later on when more resources are available.
Usually, process recovery is a costly operation,
which should be avoided to the extent possible.
As always, nonetheless, the exact costs
of each alternative (including both
proactive and reactive ones) will depend
on the specific case taken into account!